Finding Aid for A. Alfred Taubman College of Architecture + Urban Planning Records 1876-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Architectural Drawings
  The Architectural Drawings series captures in a wide range of drawing types, visions for the housing of the college in Ann Arbor from the mid-1940s to the very recent past. Carefully executed perspectives and elevations in pencil on tracing paper (signed RCG) represent a proposed 1946 addition for the Central Campus location of College of Architecture and Design. Eight undated blackline prints entitled "A Proposed Building by Associated Architects, The Department of Architecture Staff," positions the college on North Campus, but on a site that was not to be. Fifteen design development drawings in pencil and marker on vellum by Della Sala, Olencki, Sanders and Associates, 1955, also document an unbuilt North Campus project. (The North Campus building was eventually designed by Robert S. Swanson & Associates and completed in 1974.) The most recent envisioned design for expansion and alteration of the current building is in a file entitled Program for Regeneration: University of Michigan Art and Architecture Building. In 1997, Enrique Norten and his firm TEN Arquitectos presented nine proposals to faculty, six were developed in more detail, and one selected by Alfred Taubman, benefactor of the project. The program for the regeneration project and related textual materials are in Box 45.
  - Geodesic Dome Camp Shelter. Built under the direction of Buckminster Fuller 1954, 4 blueprints
    - Project Scheme (Map-case 1)
    - Five Basic Rapt Sections (Map-case 1)
    - Base Details (Map-case 1)
    - Pent Cap Details (Map-case 1)
  - Addition Proposed for College of Architecture & Design (signed RCG)
    - Perspectives 1946, pencil on tracing paper
      - Court perspective, First study (Map-case 1)
      - East perspective (Map-case 1)
      - Lobby, First study (Map-case 1)
      - Perspective, Fifth study (Map-case 1)
      - Schematic Design, Fifth study (Map-case 1)
      - South court elevation, First study; Second study, 2 drawings (Map-case 1)
      - South elevation, First-Sixth study, 6 drawings (Map-case 1)
      - South perspective (Map-case 1)
      - Street perspectives; First study; Second study, 2 drawings (Map-case 1)
      - West elevation, First-Fourth study, 4 drawings (Map-case 1)
    - South perspective 1954, pencil on tracing paper (Map-case 1)
  - College of Architecture and Design Building. Della Sala, Olencki, Sanders Associates
    - Design Development Drawings circa 1955, pencil on vellum
      - Plot plan (Map-case 1)
      - Ground floor plan (Map-case 1)
      - Mezzanine floor plan (Map-case 1)
      - Studio floor plan (Map-case 1)
      - Elevations (Map-case 1)
      - Sections (Map-case 1)
      - Perspectives, 2 drawings (Map-case 1)
  - A Proposed Building. Associated Architects, The Department of Architecture Staff
    - Design development drawings undated, blackline prints except as noted
      - Site Plan, 2 prints (Map-case 1)
      - Floor plans, 3 prints (Map-case 1)
      - Elevations and Sections, 2 prints (Map-case 1)
      - Perspective (pencil on paper) (Map-case 1)
  - Program for Regeneration, University of Michigan Art and Architecture Building. Ten Arquitectos
    (see also program and proposal in box 45)
    - Computer Aided Design (CAD) Drawings 1997, black and white presentation prints on paper, some with colored marker
      - Presentation One: Nine Proposals
        - Program (Map-case 1)
        - Analysis Areas/Uses, 2 prints (Map-case 1)
        - Consistencies (Map-case 1)
        - Floor Plans and Presentation Drawings
          - Covered Courtyard (Map-case 1)
          - Basement Public Areas (Map-case 1)
          - Bridge Building (Map-case 1)
          - Office Tower (Map-case 1)
          - Perpendicular West Building (Map-case 1)
          - Central Axis Connector (Map-case 1)
          - New South Building (Map-case 1)
          - Expansion of Existing Areas (Map-case 1)
          - "L" Shape Building (Map-case 1)
      - Presentation Two: Six Proposals
        - Area and Square Footage Charts, 6 prints (Map-case 1)
        - Six Proposals for Regeneration (program) (Map-case 1)
        - Analysis Areas/Uses, 2 prints (Map-case 1)
        - Consistencies (Map-case 1)
        - Six Proposals (Map-case 1)
          (presentation on one sheet)
        - Site Plan and Covered Courtyard, 2 prints (Map-case 1)
        - Site Plan and Perpendicular West Building (Map-case 1)
        - Site Plan and Basement Public Areas, 2 prints (Map-case 1)
        - Site Plan and Bridge Building, 2 prints (Map-case 1)
        - Site Plan and Expansion of Existing Areas, 2 prints (Map-case 1)
        - Site Plan and "L" Shape Building, 2 prints (Map-case 1)
      - Presentation Three: Final Proposal
        - Uses (Map-case 1)
        - Exploded Isometric (Map-case 1)
        - Site Plan (Map-case 1)
        - Floor Plans, 2 prints (Map-case 1)
        - Sections and Elevations, 2 prints (Map-case 1)
        - Presentation Models, 2 prints (Map-case 1)
        - Perspectives, 2 prints (Map-case 1)
  - Art and Architecture Building Floor Plans, unsigned undated, 3 marker on vellum drawings (Map-case 1)
  - Studio Layouts, unsigned 1977, 1979, 1984, 1986, 4 marker and pencil on tracing paper drawings (Map-case 1)
- Photographs and Negatives
  - Photographs (Early Accessions)
    The Photographs series include a wonderful group of images, many taken by Emil Lorch in 1926, documenting the construction of the Architecture and Design building that was named in his honor. There are also photographs of Buckminster Fuller's Dymaxion Dome. Fuller assembled the dome with the help of a design class in 1954. There is a set of very fine black and white photographs of faculty mounted on boards that were part of a 1968 exhibit entitled, "Faculty Exhibit Work." There is also a set of copy negatives produced from an equally fine set of undated faculty portraits. (The portraits were photographed because they could not safely be removed from large, heavy boards.) Also included in the series is a zip disk holding digital versions of images reproduced in Nancy Bartlett's history of the college, More Than a Handsome Box. An oversized box of photographs holds a striking Emil Lorch portrait; class of 1927 reunion snapshots; and several beautiful large photographs of Lorch Hall.
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Wallenberg Lecture Series
      - Larrabee, Eric (Box 4)
      - Pevsner, Nikolaus (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Art and Architecture Groundbreaking Ceremony 1972 (Box 25)
    - Art and Architecture Library undated (Box 25)
    - Cranbrook, George Booth Estate undated (Box 25)
    - R. Buckminster Fuller and his Dymaxion Dome 1954 (Box 25)
    - William LeBaron Jenney undated (Box 25)
    - Kappa Beta Psi undated (Box 25)
    - Emil Lorch College of Architecture and Design Building
      (see also oversized Box 49)
      - Model circa 1926 (Box 25)
      - Site circa 1926 (Box 25)
      - Construction circa 1926 (Box 25)
      - Exterior circa 1926 (Box 25)
      - Garden circa 1926 (Box 25)
      - Interior (Box 25)
      - Library (Box 25)
      - Unistrut (Box 25)
    - "M" Room at Yost Field House 1947 (Box 25)
    - Exhibit Boards:"Faculty Exhibit Work," 1968
      - Joseph Akerman (Box 48)
      - Joseph Albano (Box 48)
      - Norman Barnett (Box 48)
      - Gunnar Birkerts (Box 48)
      - Jacques C. Brownson (Box 48)
      - Robert D. Carpenter (Box 48)
      - Daniel Carson (Box 48)
      - James Costello (Box 48)
      - J. Sterling Crandall (Box 48)
      - Gerald E. Crane (Box 48)
      - Robert M. Darvas (Box 48)
      - William Drake (Box 48)
      - Leonard K. Eaton (Box 48)
      - Bruce E. Erickson (Box 48)
      - Lester Fader (Box 48)
      - Benjamin Handler (Box 48)
      - Harold Himes (Box 48)
      - John W. Hyde (Box 48)
      - Herbert W. Johe (Box 48)
      - C. Theodore Larson (Box 48)
      - Joseph T.A. Lee (Box 48)
      - Robert B. Lytle (Box 48)
      - Reginald F. Malcolmson (Box 48)
      - Glenn G. Mastin (Box 48)
      - Robert C. Metcalf (Box 48)
      - William Muschenheim (Box 48)
      - Gerhard Olving (Box 48)
      - Edward V. Olencki (Box 48)
      - S.C.A. Paraskevopoulos (Box 48)
      - Walter Sanders (Box 48)
      - Carl V. Schmult Jr. (Box 48)
      - F. Peter Seidel (Box 48)
      - Joseph J. Wehrer (Box 48)
    - Portraits undated
      (Includes biographical briefs, 4x5 black and white negatives, and positive printouts of scanned negatives)
      - Joseph F. Albano (Box 48)
      - Gunnar G. Birkerts (Box 48)
      - Roger D. Clemence (Box 48)
      - Robert M. Darvas (Box 48)
      - Leonard K. Eaton (Box 48)
      - Bruce E. Erickson (Box 48)
      - Lester Fader (Box 48)
      - Martin D. Gehner (Box 48)
      - James Haecker (Box 48)
      - Ralph W. Hammett (Box 48)
      - Benjamin Handler (Box 48)
      - Harold W. Himes (Box 48)
      - John Worthington Hyde (Box 48)
      - Herbert W. Johe (Box 48)
      - C. Theodore Larson (Box 48)
      - Joseph T. A. Lee (Box 48)
      - Robert Bruce Lytle, Jr. (Box 48)
      - Glenn G. Mastin (Box 48)
      - Robert C. Metcalf (Box 48)
      - William Muschenheim (Box 48)
      - Edward V. Olencki (Box 48)
      - Stephen C. A. Paraskevopoulos (Box 48)
      - Walter B. Sanders (Box 48)
      - Joseph Wehrer (Box 48)
      - Philip Newell Youtz (Box 48)
    - Faculty Portraits undated (Box 48)
      (Mainly 2 x 3 b&w photographic prints; includes three 8 x 10s: Wells Bennett and 2 of Philip Youtz)
    - More Than a Handsome Box, 3 zip disks (Box 48)
      (Digital images utilized in publication by Nancy Bartlett) (Macintosh EPS format files on 3 Zip disks)
    - Reunions
      - 1927 Architects
        - 20th Class Reunion 1947 (Box 48)
        - 30th Class Reunion 1957 (Box 48)
        - 35th Class Reunion 1962 (Box 48)
        - 45th Class Reunion 1972 (Box 48)
        - 50th Class Reunion 1977 (Box 48)
        - "College Days" (Box 48)
          (photographs removed from reunion poster)
        - "Old Grad Activities" (Box 48)
    - Lorch Hall undated, black and white photographs, ca. 11x13 (Box 49)
      - "Architecture Building" (Interior hallway) (Box 49)
      - "Architecture Building" (Interior and view from window) (Box 49)
      - "Court of Architecture" (Box 49)
      - "Garden of Architecture Building", 2 folders (Box 49)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Malcolmson, Reginald photograph of rendering undated (Box 49)
      - Group portrait, unidentified undated (Box 49)
    - "Lorch, Emil," undated, 16 x 20 black and white (Box 49)
    - Classes (Box 49)
      (Includes 1927 1980 and 1981 group portraits)
  - Photographs and Negatives circa 1970-2004, 1987-2004
    The Photographs and Negatives series (7 linear feet) continues the series from previous accessions. The majority of the images date from 1987 to 2004, but there are earlier images dating from as far back as the 1920's/1930's to 1986. The series has been divided into six sub-series: Binders; Buildings and Other Structures; Events and Programs; People; Projects; and Publications. There is some overlap between sub-series.
    Included in this series are photos of exhibits, commencements, notable visitors to the college, alumni, buildings and structures designed by faculty and alumni, and images used to illustrate TCAUP publications. Of note are images of the Detroit Charettes held in 1999, 2000, 2001, and 2002 (located in two sub-series: Binders, and Events and Programs), and from the naming ceremony held to celebrate the endowment from A. Alfred Taubman and the renaming of the college in his honor. Other significant images include a memento to Buckminster Fuller's geodesic dome, the dedication of the Wallenberg memorial in front of the school, and a nice set of faculty photos from 1981 that include brief CV's attached to each portrait. Finally, the series provides a nice sampling of student work from classes, exhibits, and competitions.
    Researchers should note that the Binders sub-series is unique from the other sub-series in organization. The materials in this sub-series were originally housed in binders. Most of the binders contained a combination of photos from various events, projects, people, and structures that were housed together according to year, or month and year. There were also a number of binders containing images relating to a specific event, such as the charrettes of 2001 and 2002. The materials in each binder were kept together and re-housed in expandable folders. Therefore, the labels for these folders will be much broader than the folders labels used in the other sub-series, and researchers will find materials from multiple events and activities in these folders.
    Researchers should also note that some folders in the series included image identification forms containing descriptive information on the images included in that file. These forms were part of a project to describe the images before they were sent to the Bentley, and the information on some of these forms may not be accurate.
    - Binders
      - General Photos
        - Architecture Student Show 2000 (Box 73)
        - Charrette
          - 2001 (Box 73)
          - 2002 (Box 73)
        - Naming Ceremony October 13, 1999 (Box 73)
        - Student Work: Student Exhibits, Drawings and Models 1999 (Box 73)
        - "Taking Aim" -- Student Exhibit 1998 (Box 73)
        - Taubman College Photos November 2000, 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 73)
          (includes CD containing photos, and prints, by Christopher Campbell)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 74)
          - 1991-1996 (Box 74)
            (also called "Historical Photos")
          - 1996-1997 (Box 74)
          - 1998
            - January-August (Box 74)
            - September-December (Box 74)
          - 1999 (Box 75)
            - January-September, 2 folders (Box 75)
            - October-December (Box 75)
          - 2000
            - May-December (Box 75)
          - 2001
            - January-April (Box 75)
            - May-December (Box 75)
    - Buildings and Other Structures
      - Art and Architecture Building
        - Exterior (Box 76)
          - Aerial Photos, no date (Box 76)
          - Miscellaneous circa 1987-1996 (scattered) (Box 76)
        - Interior
          - Computer Lab in Studio 1995 (Box 76)
          - Woodshop, no date (Box 76)
      - International
        - Aarhus Universitet, Denmark June 1985 (Box 76)
      - Michigan, State of
        - Cappon House Museum, Holland, MI 2001 (Box 76)
          (ornament designed by two TCAUP alumni)
        - Hart Plaza, Detroit, MI, no date (Box 76)
        - Norris House, Detroit, MI, no date (Box 76)
      - United States
        - Muschenheim House, Long Island, NY circa 1995 (Box 76)
        - Solar House, Princeton, NJ, no date (designed by Doug Kelbaugh) (Box 76)
        - Storage Technology Corporation Conference Center, CO 1992 (Box 76)
        - Temple Judea Holocaust Research Center, Manhasset, NY 1992 (Box 76)
      - University of Michigan
        - Lorch Hall, no date (Box 76)
        - North Campus Bell Tower -- model (Ann and Robert H. Lurie Tower) circa 1993 (Box 76)
    - Events and Programs
      - Alumni Events
        - Alumni Go Abroad (Florence, Italy) 1995 (Box 76)
        - Alumni Meeting in Tokyo, Japan September 1993 (Box 76)
        - Alumni Reception/Scholars and Patrons Dinner 1995-1996 (Box 76)
        - Alumni Reunion
          - Fall 1988 (Box 76)
          - 1990 (Box 76)
        - Alumni Reunion, and Scholars and Patrons Dinner 2002 (CD only; no prints) (Box 76)
        - Alumni Reunion Weekend 1988-1989 (Box 76)
        - Scholars and Patrons Dinner
          - October 1992 (Box 76)
          - January 12, 1994 (Box 76)
          - March 10, 2001 (Box 76)
        - Scholars and Patrons Luncheons September 1989, October 1990 (Box 76)
      - Charrettes
        - Cass Corridor 1999
          - General, 2 folders (Box 76)
          - Drawings (negatives (Box 76)
          - General Office Auditorium (Box 76)
          - Pre-Charrette Dinner at Union St. Station (Box 76)
          - Team Presentations -- Drawings (Box 76)
        - Michigan at Trumbull 2000
          - General, 2 folders (Box 76)
          - Buildings/Sites (Box 76)
          - Drawings (negatives) (Box 76)
          - Team Presentations (Box 76)
      - Commemorative Events
        - Memento of Buckminster Fuller's Geodesic Dome (40th Anniversary) 1994 (Box 77)
        - Wallenberg Sculpture Dedication October 26, 1995 (Box 77)
      - Commencement
        - Spring 1990 (Box 77)
        - May 3, 1997 (Box 77)
        - April 27, 2002 (Box 77)
      - Competitions
        - Albert Kahn Associates (AKA) Fellowship 1994 (Box 77)
        - Alumni Society Awards
          - 1994 (Box 77)
          - 1996 (Box 77)
        - Burnham Prize 1995 (Box 77)
        - Camp Michigania Bell Tower Competition 1988 (Box 77)
        - "Harboursite: Exploring the Element" Competition (Copper Technology Center design) 1995 (Box 77)
        - Kiefer Traveling Fellowship 1994 (Box 77)
        - Perez Scholarship 1989-1990 (Box 77)
        - Wallenberg Competition
          - 1988-1990 (Box 77)
          - 1993 (Box 77)
          - 1994 (Box 77)
          - 1995 (Box 77)
      - Willeke Competition
        - No date (Box 77)
        - 1988-1991 (Box 77)
        - March 1993 (Box 77)
        - 1994 (Box 77)
      - Exhibits
        - "40/40" Photo Exhibition (Balthazar Korab Exhibit) 1997 (Box 77)
        - Architectural Renderings: 1893 World's Columbian Exposition, 1993-1994 (work by students of Professor Emeritus Herbert W. Johe) (Box 77)
        - Architecture Program Student Exhibit/Show
          - February 1993 (Box 77)
          - January 1994 (Box 77)
          - February 1995 (Box 77)
          - February 1996 (Box 77)
          - 1997 (Box 77)
          - 2000 (Box 77)
          - January-February 2002 (Box 77)
        - "Best of Show" -- Wallenberg Competition February 1993 (Box 77)
        - "Buildings in the City: Recent Projects in Mexico" -- Exhibit and Gallery Talk by Enrique Norton and TEN Arquitectos February-March 1997 (Box 77)
        - Constructs -- Architecture Program Student Exhibit February 1997, 2 folders (Box 77)
        - "House" -- Faculty and Student Exhibition October 1995 (Box 77)
        - Mangurian-Ray Wrapper Exhibit January 2002 (Box 77)
        - Martin Luther King, Jr. Day Exhibit 1997 (Box 77)
        - "Merging Two Realities" Exhibition, Roto Architects March 1996 (Box 77)
        - "Morphosis: Silent Collisions," October 1995 (Box 77)
        - "Orders of Architecture," 1994 (exhibit outside of the University in which Professor Emeritus Herbert W. Johe participated; he also delivered a lecture: "Architectural Renderings in Watercolor: Preparation and Process") (Box 77)
        - Paktau Architects Exhibit March-April 1995 (Box 77)
        - "Portugal of Sea, Stone and Cities," Joao Carillo de Graca February 1997 (Box 77)
        - Prague Exhibit: Through its Endless Inside, Winter 2000 (Box 77)
        - "Stalking Detroit" -- work by the Committee for Urban Thinking: Detroit November-December 1997 (Box 77)
        - Student Exhibit (photos of models) circa 2000 (Box 77)
        - Structures and Surfaces Exhibit September-November 1992 (Box 77)
        - "Tokyo Forum," Rafael Vinoly -- John Dinkeloo Memorial Lecture and Exhibit February 1997 (Box 77)
        - Urban and Region Planning (URP) Student/Faculty Work Exhibit February 1997 (Box 77)
        - Vincent James Exhibit (Binda Lecture and Exhibit) March 2000 (Box 77)
      - International Programs
        - Czech-American Studio, Spring 1992 (Box 77)
        - Florence Program 1996 (Box 77)
        - Vienna Exchange Program, Fall 1990 (Box 77)
      - Lectures
        - Eisenman, Peter, "Seeing Architecture," November 21, 1997 (Box 77)
        - Gavin, Alexander, "The American City: What Works, What Doesn't," November 7, 1996 (Box 77)
        - Forbes, Peter, "Our Work and Modernism" (Guido A. Binda Lecture) April 11, 1997 (Box 77)
        - McFarlane Lecture March 24, 2000 (Box 77)
        - Noero, Jo (visiting lecturer) January 17, 1996 (Box 77)
        - North Campus Redux Lecture, Doug Kelbaugh October 7, 2002 (includes zip disk and CD), 1 optical disks CDs; 1 zip disks (Box 77)
        - Rybczynski, Witold, "What Kind of Cities Do We Need?," February 21, 1997 (Box 77)
        - Wallenberg Lecture
          - Michael Sorkin March 26, 1997 (Box 77)
          - Michael Benedikt 2000 (also includes photos of other related events) (Box 77)
      - Presentations
        - Community Outreach Presentation -- SW Detroit Business Association (Professor Margaret Dewar's class) December 1997 (Box 77)
        - Ghana Studio, Spring 2002 (Box 77)
        - Standard Products Presentation, no date (Box 77)
      - Student Activities
        - Beaux-Arts Ball March 2000 (Box 77)
        - Habitat for Humanity 1994-1996 (Box 77)
        - TCAUP Picnic, Fall 2002 (includes a zip disk), 1 zip disks (Box 77)
      - Miscellaneous
        - ACSA 1975 Dedication Day, April 9, 1975 Producers Council, February 12, 1975, 2 folders (Box 78)
        - Detroit Public Schools visit TCAUP 2000 (Box 78)
        - Meeting with Daniel Libeskind February 1995 (Box 78)
        - Reception for Dean Robert Beckley June 28, 1997 (Box 78)
        - Exhibits and Visitors circa 1995-1998 (Ken Faulkner; Jack Travis; Borom/Wamoto Exhibit) (Box 78)
        - Summer Discovery Program
          - 1995 (Box 78)
          - 1997 (Box 78)
        - Urban and Regional Planning (URP) Program Open House March 1997 (Box 78)
    - People
      - Alumni
        - Cutter, Nancy Lickerman 1996 (Box 78)
        - Jonsson, Maggie circa 1970s-1980s (Box 78)
          (includes images of buildings he worked on in Iceland)
        - King, Lorraine Dale 1992 (Box 78)
        - Mikon, Arnold, no date (Box 78)
        - Parston, Greg and Parston, Mark E.P. 1995 (Box 78)
        - Sirefman, Josh, no date (Box 78)
        - Taubman, A. Alfred, no date (Box 78)
        - Tincknell, Leslie 1996 (Box 78)
        - Tosumer, Renda, no date (Box 78)
      - Faculty and Staff
        - Faculty of 1981 (photos attached to brief CV's) (Box 78)
        - Fellows Work: Glenn Wilcox and Karl Daubmann April 2000 (Box 78)
        - Individual Faculty
          - Beckley, Robert (Bob) circa 1997 (Box 78)
          - Chaffers, Jim, no date (Box 78)
          - Dandekar, Hemalata C.
            - Going Away Lunch, Winter 2002 (Box 78)
            - Portrait 1994 (Box 78)
          - Darvas, Robert M. 1996 (Box 78)
          - Feldt, Allan G. 1996 (Box 78)
          - Kelbaugh, Doug circa 1999-2000, 1 zip disks (Box 78)
            (includes a zip disk)
          - King, Jonathan 1986 (Box 78)
          - Thomas, June, no date (Box 78)
          - Warner, Kate 2002 (Box 78)
            (includes portrait and retirement party photos)
        - Miscellaneous, no date (Box 78)
      - Groups and Organizations
        - Americorps Members 1996 (Box 78)
        - Architecture and Urban Planning Cabinet, Summer 1987 (Box 78)
        - Hockey Team 1996 (Box 78)
        - Mayor's Institute on City Design June 2002 (zip disk included) (Box 78)
      - Students
        - Career Discovery Participants circa 1990s (Box 78)
        - McCray, Talia 1999 (Box 78)
        - Miscellaneous
          - circa 1920-1950 (Box 78)
          - circa 1980-1990 (Box 78)
          - 1987 (Box 78)
          - 2000 (Box 78)
        - "Roman Holiday" Architects' Ball (Irene Sartor and Ralph Rapson) circa 1937-1938 (Box 78)
        - Wallenberg, Raoul (pictured at Architects' Ball with Bernice Ringman) circa 1930s (Box 78)
      - Visiting Lecturers, Professors, and Scholars